Adela C. Breton Papers 1915-1923 Mss.B.B754
American Philosophical Society
Adela C. Breton Papers
1915-1923
Mss.B.B754
American Philosophical Society
0.1 Linear feet
Having inherited a fortune from her father, the middle-aged Adela C. Breton (1849-1923) began to indulge her interest in travel and archaeology. Between 1894 and 1908, Breton took thirteen excursions to the Mayan archaeological sites in Yucatan, Mexico, researching the artwork and producing valuable watercolor paintings of the ruins. She died in 1923, during a trip to attend the International Congress of Americanists in Rio de Janeiro. The Breton Papers consist of one hundred letters written by Adela Breton to her friend and relative Ella Lewis of Philadelphia. Although they offer little insight into Breton's archaeological interests, they do provide a glimpse of her personality and her opinions on everything from American immigration law to the First World War, the malice of Germans, and her experiences traveling in western Canada.
Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
Bibliography
Giles, Sue and Jennifer Stewart, eds., The Art of Ruins: Miss Adela Breton and the Temples of Mexico Catalogue for an exhibition, December 1989 to March 1990 (City of Bristol Museum and Art Gallery, Bristol, 1989).
Existence and Location of Originals note
The originals of the Breton Papers are now housed at the Peabody Museum of Archaeology and Ethnology, Harvard University (Accession no. 976-63, 45-5, 2001.7).
Related Archival Materials note
The Franz Boas Papers (Mss.B.B61) contain 15 letters between Boas and Breton, 1907-1912, mostly relating to Breton's work for the 18th International Congress of Americanists.
The Bristol City Museum and Art Gallery houses a collection of Adela Breton's watercolors of Mayan archaeological sites in Mexico.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The photocopies were donated to the APS by Clifford Lewis III, grandson of Ella Lewis, in 1976 (accn. 1977-1077ms).
Scope and Contents note
The Breton collection consists of photocopies of 100 letters addressed to Ella Lewis of Philadelphia, Adela C. Breton's friend and relative. Purely personal in nature, 94 of these were written by Breton, and 6 (all written after her death) by her brother Harry, and although they offer little insight into Breton's archaeological or artistic interests, they do provide a glimpse of her personality and her opinions on everything from American immigration law to the First World War, the malice of Germans, and her experiences traveling in western Canada.
Biographical/Historical note
With the financial independence gained through an inheritance from her father in 1887, Adela C. Breton began to pursue her interests in travel and archaeology. Born into a well to do family in Bath, England, in 1849, Breton had never married, spending most of her adult life caring for her ailing parents. However with the death of her father, she tossed aside her home-bound life for over thirty five years of almost continual travel, wedding trips for pleasure with a growing professional involvement in Mesoamerican archaeology.
Between 1894 and 1908, the intrepid Breton took thirteen excursions to archaeological sites in Yucatan, where she became an important part of the budding Mayanist community. Alfred P. Maudsley encouraged her to use her skills as a watercolorist to document the fragile and rapidly deteriorating archaeological sites, and her illustrations of Chichén Itzá (especially the Temple of Jaguars), Acancéh, and Teotihuacán provide irreplaceable evidence of the original colors and appearance of the murals and other artwork. Breton also contributed work on Mayan languages and was an energetic contributor to professional organizations, particularly the International Congress of Americanists. Although health was often an issue during the last decade of her life, she continued to travel well into her seventies. In 1923, however, after attending the International Congress of Americanists in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, she fell ill and died, leaving her brother in shock. "For the last 30 years and more," he wrote, "Adela has so often left England and returned safe if not sound that it is only the sight of her watch on a table in the dining room here that makes me realize that she will never come back from Rio -- that fatal trip."
Breton, Harry Dietrich; Lewis, Ella; Canada--Description and travel.; Women archaeologists; World War, 1914-1918
- Adela C. Breton Papers, 1915-1923 (Box 1)
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1915 Jan. 6; 2p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1915 March 14; 2p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, [1915] May 14; 1p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, [1915] July 23; 1p. (fragment); Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, [1915] Aug. 6; 2p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, [1915] Aug. 13; 1p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, [1915 summer]; 1p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1915 September 23; 2p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1915 September 29; 7p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1915 October 18-19; 6p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1915 December 4; 2p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1916 January 23-24; 5p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1916 February 14; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1916 March 3; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1916 March 14; 2p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1916 March 27; 2p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1916 April 21; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1916 May 9; 1p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1916 May 19; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1916 July 14; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1916 August 1; 2p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1916 August 18; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1916 September 5; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1916 September 27; 6p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1916 October 22; 7p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1916 November 12; 3p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1916 November 26; 6p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1917 January 5-6; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1917 January 22; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1917 February 4; 2p. (inc.); Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1917 February 19; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1917 March 10; 6p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1917 March 30; 5p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1917 April 19; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1917 May 16; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1917 June 9-10; 6p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1917 June 23; 7p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1917 July 17; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1917 August 10; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1917 August 29; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1917 September 14; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1917 October 5; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1917 October 12; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1917 October 29; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1917 November 11-12; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1917 November 23; 6p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1917 December 6; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1917 December 12; 8p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1917 December 28; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1918 January 18; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1918 February 3-7; 6p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1918 March 13; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1918 April 28; 3p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1918 June 8; 5p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1918 June 24; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1918 July 8; 2p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1918 July 21; 6p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1918 August 8; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1918 August 23; 3p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1918 August 27; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1918 September 17; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1918 October 9; 1p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1918 October 17; 2p. (plus enclosure); Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1918 November 7; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1918 November 20; 2p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1918 December 13; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1918 December 26; 3p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1919 January 14; 2p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1919 February 12; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1919 March 5; 2p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1919 April 25; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1919 May 27; 3p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1919 July 3; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1919 September 2; 2p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1919 September 8; 2p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1919 November 23; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1919 December 31; 2p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1920 January 6; 2p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1920 January 21; 2p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1920 February 14; 2p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1920 March 13; 3p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1920 March 27; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1920 May 7; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1920 July 4; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, [1920] September 23; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1920 November 8; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1921 January 3; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1921 June 27; 8p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1921 September 13; 6p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1921 November 5; 2p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1921 December 17; 4p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1922 March 10; 6p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1922 August 10; 6p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1922 September 17; 6p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1922 December 26; 2p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1923 June 16; 2p.; Breton, Adela, 1849-1923
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1923 July 2; 1p.; Breton, Harry Dietrich
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1923 July 25; 3p.; Breton, Harry Dietrich
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1923 September 7; 3p.; Breton, Harry Dietrich
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1923 October 9; 2p.; Breton, Harry Dietrich
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1923 December 31; 1p.; Breton, Harry Dietrich
  - ALS Cy to Ella Lewis, 1924 March 3; 2p.; Breton, Harry Dietrich